<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Wouter Haverals</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Wouter Haverals</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.145.0</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Carthusian Digital Archive</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/project-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projects/project-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;carthusian-digital-archive-herne-manuscript-collection&#34;&gt;Carthusian Digital Archive: Herne Manuscript Collection&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project involved leading the digital transcription and analysis of the complete manuscript collection from the Carthusian monastery of Herne (14th century). This comprehensive digital archive makes accessible an important corpus of Middle Dutch texts that have significant historical and linguistic value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;historical-significance&#34;&gt;Historical Significance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Carthusian monastery of Herne was a major center for manuscript production and translation in the 14th century, responsible for introducing numerous Latin works to the Low Countries through vernacular translations. These manuscripts represent a crucial phase in the development of scholarly Middle Dutch and reflect important cultural exchanges in medieval Europe.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CATMuS: Multilingual HTR Dataset</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/project-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projects/project-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;catmus-multilingual-dataset-for-htr-research&#34;&gt;CATMuS: Multilingual Dataset for HTR Research&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I contributed the Middle Dutch component to CATMuS (Comprehensive Archive of Transcribed Multilingual Sources), a pioneering multilingual dataset for Handwritten Text Recognition (HTR) research across European languages. This collaborative project brings together manuscript data from multiple languages, periods, and scribal traditions to enable more robust cross-lingual HTR research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-challenge&#34;&gt;The Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Handwritten Text Recognition systems have traditionally been developed for specific languages or even specific manuscript collections, limiting their applicability across the diversity of historical documents. CATMuS was created to address this fragmentation by providing a standardized, comprehensive dataset spanning multiple languages.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CERberus: HTR Evaluation Tool</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/projects/project-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/projects/project-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;cerberus-handwritten-text-recognition-evaluation-tool&#34;&gt;CERberus: Handwritten Text Recognition Evaluation Tool&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CERberus is an open-source tool I designed and implemented for evaluating Handwritten Text Recognition (HTR) systems. The project was nominated for Best DH Tool in 2023 and has become an important resource for digital humanities researchers working with historical manuscripts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;challenge&#34;&gt;Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evaluating the quality of automated transcriptions from historical manuscripts is complex, requiring specialized metrics that account for historical spelling variations, scribal abbreviations, and language-specific features. Existing tools were either too simplistic (focusing only on Character Error Rate) or too specialized for broader adoption.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Teaching</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/teaching/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;teaching-philosophy--courses&#34;&gt;Teaching Philosophy &amp;amp; Courses&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My teaching integrates digital methods with traditional humanities scholarship, creating opportunities for students to engage with historical texts and cultural heritage through both close and distant reading approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;current-courses&#34;&gt;Current Courses&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;display: flex; align-items: flex-start; margin-bottom: 20px;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div style=&#34;flex: 3;&#34;&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;Introduction to Digital Humanities: Spring 2024&lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Princeton University, Spring 2024&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;This introductory course explores how computational methods can enhance humanities research. Students engage with:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Fundamentals of digital text analysis&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Network analysis for cultural and historical data&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Data visualization techniques for humanities questions&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Critical approaches to AI and machine learning in humanities research&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div style=&#34;flex: 1; margin-left: 20px; max-width: 120px;&#34;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/classlogo-spring24.png&#34; alt=&#34;Spring 2024 DH Class Logo&#34; style=&#34;width: 100%; height: auto; object-fit: contain;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;display: flex; align-items: flex-start; margin-bottom: 20px;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div style=&#34;flex: 3;&#34;&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;Introduction to Digital Humanities: Fall 2024&lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Princeton University, Fall 2024&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;hello-im-wouter-haverals&#34;&gt;Hello, I&amp;rsquo;m Wouter Haverals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a researcher and software engineer working at the intersection of computational methods and literary-historical research. My work focuses on creating innovative approaches to study cultural heritage through digital humanities methodologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;professional-focus&#34;&gt;Professional Focus&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My work spans the intersection of computational methods and literary-historical research, creating innovative approaches to study cultural heritage. I focus on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Applying digital humanities methodologies to historical texts across languages and time periods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developing open-source tools for manuscript analysis and transcription&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building bridges between traditional philological scholarship and computational approaches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exploring patterns of textual transmission and literary development through data-driven methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Democratizing access to cultural heritage through digital frameworks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;skills&#34;&gt;Skills&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;experience-highlights&#34;&gt;Experience Highlights&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Designed and implemented CERberus, an open-source tool for evaluating HTR systems (nominated for Best DH Tool, 2023)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Led the digital transcription of the complete manuscript collection from the Carthusian monastery of Herne (14th century)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Served as Programme Chair for the Computational Humanities Research Conference 2024&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contributed the Middle Dutch component to CATMuS, a multilingual dataset for HTR research across European languages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developed innovative computational approaches to analyze medieval poetic meter and rhythm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;education&#34;&gt;Education&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PhD in Language and Literature, University of Antwerp (2019)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Master of Arts in Language and Literature, University of Antwerp (2014, Magna Cum Laude)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teacher Training Program, University of Antwerp (2015, Magna Cum Laude)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bachelor of Arts in Dutch and English Language and Literature, University of Antwerp (2013, Cum Laude)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exchange Program, Hamilton High School, Wisconsin, USA (2009-2010)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;connect&#34;&gt;Connect&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m always interested in new collaborations at the intersection of humanities and technology. Whether you&amp;rsquo;re working on manuscript digitization, computational literary analysis, or exploring new applications of AI for cultural heritage, I&amp;rsquo;d love to discuss potential projects and partnerships.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital Approaches to Medieval Manuscripts</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/my-first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/my-first-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;digital-approaches-to-medieval-manuscripts&#34;&gt;Digital Approaches to Medieval Manuscripts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The intersection of digital technologies and historical manuscript studies has opened new horizons for understanding our textual heritage. As someone working in this interdisciplinary space, I&amp;rsquo;d like to share some reflections on the challenges and opportunities of applying computational methods to medieval texts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-digital-humanities-revolution&#34;&gt;The Digital Humanities Revolution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Medieval manuscript studies has undergone a transformation in recent decades through digital approaches. What was once a discipline limited by physical access to rare materials has become increasingly democratized through:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
